<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A proclamation against the vnreuere[n]t disputers and talkers of the sacramente of the body and blood of Christ commonly called the sacrament of the aultar, set furth by the Kynges Maiestie, with thassente and co[n]sent of his most deere vncle, Edwarde Duke of Somerset, gouernour of his moste royall person, and of hys realmes, dominio[n]s and subiectes protector, and other of hys highnes most honorable pryuey counsaill, the .xxvii. daye of Decembre, in the first yeare of his Maiesties most gratious reigne.</title>
            <title>Proclamations. 1547-12-27</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1547-1553 : Edward VI)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1547</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A69315</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7812</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109330</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844980</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844980</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9840</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A69315)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9840)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 10:24, 152:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A proclamation against the vnreuere[n]t disputers and talkers of the sacramente of the body and blood of Christ commonly called the sacrament of the aultar, set furth by the Kynges Maiestie, with thassente and co[n]sent of his most deere vncle, Edwarde Duke of Somerset, gouernour of his moste royall person, and of hys realmes, dominio[n]s and subiectes protector, and other of hys highnes most honorable pryuey counsaill, the .xxvii. daye of Decembre, in the first yeare of his Maiesties most gratious reigne.</title>
                  <title>Proclamations. 1547-12-27</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1547-1553 : Edward VI)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>2 leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In ædibus Richardi Graftoni regij impressoris. Cum privilegio ad imprimendum solum,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Excusum Londini :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1547]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Recites Act of 1 Edward VI against revilers of the Sacrament--Steele.</note>
                  <note>First leaf only filmed on reel 10.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Society of Antiquaries.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reels 10 and 152 (Society of Antiquaries copy).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Edward VI, 1547-1553 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="royal_proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:9840:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 8 -->
            <head>¶ A proclamation againſt the vnreuerend diſputers and talkers, of the Sacramente of the body and blood of Chriſt commonly called the Sacrament of the aultar, ſet furth by this Kyngys a<gap reason="illegible" extent="6+ letters">
                  <desc>••••••…</desc>
               </gap>ie with the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent of his moſt deere <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ncle, Edwarde Duke of <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> moſte royall perſon and of hys <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> amd ſubiectes  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>  of hys highnes moſte honorable pryuey coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saill<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> .x<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vii. daye of D<gap reason="illegible" extent="7 letters">
                  <desc>〈7 letters〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> yeare of his Maieſties moſt gratious reigne.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>here as the Kynges highnes hathe of late with thaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent of the lordes Spirituall and Temporall, and theco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in the Parliament, helde the .iiij. day of Nouember, in the firſt yeare of his moſt gracious reigne, made a good and Godly acte and eſtatute againſt thoſe, who doeth comte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pne, deſpiſe, or with vnſemely and vngodly woordes depraue and deuyle the holy Sacramente of the body and blood of our Lorde, commonly called the Sacrament of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Aultar, and in theſame eſtatute, hath moſt prudently declared by all the wordes &amp; termes, whiche ſcripture ſpeaketh of it what is vndoubtedly to be accepted, beleued, taken and ſpoken, by and of the ſayd Sacrament: Yet this notwithſtandyng, hys Maieſtie is aduertiſed, that ſome of his ſubiectes not contented with ſuche woordes and termes, as ſcripture doeth declare therof, nor with that doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, whiche the holy Ghoſte by the Euangeliſtes, and ſaincte Paule hathe taughte vs, do not ceaſe to moue contentious and ſuperfluous queſtions of the ſayde holy Sacrament and ſoupper of the Lord, entering raſhely into the diſcuſſing of the high miſtery therof, and go about in their ſermons or tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes arrogantly to defyne the maner, nature, faſhion, waies, poſſibilitie or impoſſibilitie of thoſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, whiche neither make to edification, nor God hath not by his holy worde opened: Which perſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes not contented, reuerently and with obedient faithe, to accepte that in the ſaide Sacrament, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to the ſaiyng of ſainct Paul, the bread is the communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or partaking of the body of our Lord, The wyne likewyſe the partakinge of the blood of Chriſte, by the woordes inſtituted and taughte of Chriſt and that the body and blood of Ieſu Chriſt is there, which is our comforte thankes geuing, louetoken of Chriſtes loue towardes vs &amp; of oures, as hys me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres within our ſelfe, ſearcheth &amp; ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vnreuerently whether the body and blood aforeſayd is there, really, or figuratly, locally, or circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſcriptly, and hauyng quantitie and greatnes, or but ſubſtantially, and by ſubſtaunce onely, or els but in a figure and maner of ſpeakyng, whether his bleſſed body be there head, legges, armes, toes &amp; nay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, or any other waies, ſhape &amp; maner, naked or clothed, whether he is broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ſhewed, or he is alwaies whole, whether the bread there remaineth as we ſe, or how it departeth, whether the fleſh be there alone and the blood, or parte, or eche in other, or in the one both, in the other but only blood and what blood, that onely, whiche dyd flowe out of the ſide, or that, whiche remayned, with other ſuche irreuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous and curious queſtions whiche (how, and what, and by what meanes, &amp; in what fourme) maye bring into them whiche of humaine and corrupt curioſitie, hath deſire to ſearch out ſuch miſteries, as lieth did in the infinite and botomeles deapth of the wiſedome and glory of God, and to the whiche our humaine imbecillitie cannot atteine and therfore oftetymes turneth the ſame to their awne and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers deſtruction, by contention and arrogant raſhenes: whiche ſimple and Chriſtian affection, reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently receyuing, and obediently beleuing, without further ſearch, taketh and vſeth to mooſt great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte and profite: for reformation whereof and to the intent, that further contention, tumulte &amp; que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion might not riſe emonge the kynges ſubiectes, the Kinges highnes, by the aduiſe of the lord Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector and other hys Maieſtics counſaill, ſtrayghtly willeth and commaundeth, that no manes per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, from henſf<gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>h do in any wiſe contenciouſly and openly argue, diſpute, reaſone, preach or teach, affirmyng any more termes of the ſayd bleſſed Sacrament, then be expreſſely taught in the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
